[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host adam conrad
and today as my guest is matt arbisfeld
matt arbisfeldt is a co-founder at log
rocket and a thiel fellow
log rocket was born out of he and his
co-founders frustration with
troubleshooting vague customer reported
issues
prior to log rocket matt was a student
at mit studying computer science
today matt will be sharing with us his
story of how he founded log rocket
how others can found their own companies
pivot to different ideas and how to
successfully launch a product
matt thank you so much for joining us
today on software engineering radio
thanks adam it's great to be
talking to you today very exciting i
actually entrepreneur myself and really
excited to meet with someone who is much
younger than me
and who is kicking things right out the
gate with their first company so that's
actually where i wanted it to start with
you know as a disclaimer what should we
know about survivorship bias here
because
this is a sample size of one you haven't
started really at least any companies we
know of prior to this because you
basically came from
right from mit right into this project
so i'd love to know more sort of
anything we should keep in mind here for
folks listening in
on sort of about your experience yeah i
mean this actually
is my third company okay incorporated
company so to speak
and then even within this company this
was probably the ninth idea that we came
up with so
it took many many tries to really figure
out something that worked and people
cared about so
definitely there's a survivorship bias
at play where
you know a lot of what i've learned may
not apply or is luck
but then i you know had a lot of failure
as well so don't want to discourage
people of
it takes many tries to like get
something off the ground absolutely so
i'm actually curious what were the other
two because i
the only ones i knew of was lock rocket
log is our first
c corporation so in college my friends
and i actually started two different
llc's for mobile apps that we were
building so one was a
a mobile app that let you basically have
multiple
phones that played audio at the same
time together and it was an app
we launched and then we had another
company that did a
mobile game so basically nothing kind of
in the same realm of log rocket of
business software but
did basically build some mobile games on
the side in college
okay and those you didn't raise any
money for was just you wanted to
incorporate so that you could
have a real name under it when you when
you publish those games exactly and
legal protection you know
so the the company in case you know we
did something wrong by accident the
company could kind of
bear the brunt of that that's smart even
in college knowing to lawyer up and take
care of yourselves there
that's cool great so as you just
mentioned you got your start sort of at
mit you were studying computer science
were you taking any entrepreneurship
classes like what really started that
that seed for you to go you know what i
think i wanna i don't wanna work
at google i wanna do my own thing really
the first entrepreneurship experience
went all the way back to third grade
for me and so i grew up you know my best
friend and i ben who ended up starting
company log rocket
we in third grade identified a problem
where
you'd have these desks in in class where
when you lifted the desk if you had
anything on top of the desk it all fall
off
and you had to lift it to get to your
textbooks and your pencils
so we basically invented this
contraption that would sit on your desk
a duct tape sort of water bottle holder
you put in your water bottle
and when you lifted your desk it
wouldn't fall off so that was really our
first
foray into entrepreneurship where we
would go after school we would charge
people their lunch
to basically install one of these and
you know that's kind of where we first
started
entrepreneurship you know we never
really took classes for entrepreneurship
really i focused a lot on project
classes where basically the whole time
it was just open-ended you didn't have
to sit through lectures or do homework
you would just build something
that's really where i focus a lot of my
time and found
the most rewarding i did the exact same
thing i i also studied computer science
in college and
i i 100 agree with you that the project
based
classes always felt the most rewarding
because you feel like you're building
something and it feels
most real to what you'd really want to
be doing and i would imagine especially
for someone who is
entrepreneurial and thinking of ideas
the project
based classes sort of give you two
really good signals the first
is just building stuff helps you think
of other ideas and then on top of that
you get to work with other people which
is a way in to help you find
co-founders so i'd imagine that that was
something where
intentionally or not you're sort of in
these classes going oh i kind of like
working with this person i wonder if
you know they're also interested in
mobile game development is that
something you found when you were
taking those project classes definitely
yeah and you find what skill sets are
really
you know you pair well with and sort of
where you're like oh wow there's this
whole thing
i had a friend in college who's really
really good at design and
just found wow when i was paired with a
really really strong designer we could
create incredible things so
i think it really helps identify who and
kind of what the right
pieces were to form your your founding
team
so end up being that the person i
started log market with
i didn't go to college so we didn't do
those projects but definitely learned a
lot from all those experiences of
of building things but did you go to
high school together it looked like
from you know the research i was doing
that you both went to the same high
school maybe not the same year so how
did you two meet
yeah we went to preschool together we
were born uh you know about a month
apart
our parents were best friends so really
grew up together
and went to elementary school middle
school high school
and i've stayed in touch obviously over
the years but really
you know ben was the person who
introduced me to technology and
building things so you know have a lot
to thank for just introducing me to this
whole world
and remind me was ben your co-founder if
you will of the
the desk tool that you had in third
grade oh yeah yep so you guys had a
history of
entrepreneurship from a very early age
so i'm imagining that
you know you go to different colleges
you start different things when you sort
of
come back to it being like hey i've been
thinking about this idea and
he says yeah i've been thinking about
that idea too is that kind of how it
started how did you guys sort of
reconnect on that
yeah so we were actually in san
francisco for the summer
so it was a summer internship and we
decided oh let's live together
you know i was interning at a a startup
ben was at google actually at the time
and
you know just after work we'd ideate on
ideas
some days we would just make pickles or
some kind of random activity and other
days we'd say oh
you know what are some problems that
we'd love to solve it would be
interesting to tackle so
that was really the original genesis of
log rocket was
going home ideating we had a giant white
board that we brought in and just
you know brainstorming together okay so
before i dive into that topic because
i'm i'm very interested to hear those
sort of early days while you're
because even just you saying that it
sounds exactly like this sort of silicon
valley
ideal scenario where you're you're not
in a garage but you're in the living
room you're sort of ideating on topics
it just
sounds very quaint to the the idea of
what a software engineer thinks about
when starting a company but before i get
to that
i did think about this one quote i saw
from paul graham one time where he
talked about if he could go back to
school
he would study physics instead of
computer science because he felt like
he got enough computer science education
through the programming he did on his
own because he was already passionate
about it
but he felt like if he had a different
degree then it would allow him to sort
of explore
opportunities and ideas more broadly so
if you could do it again would you still
stick with the cs degree at mit or would
you have studied something else
i think nowadays especially with so many
ideas in just pure software engineering
are covered by
software engineers that it makes a lot
of sense to
be exposed to a whole new area i don't
know physics is it but
like building spaceships or building
you know airplanes or chemical
engineering you know i think there's a
lot of different areas that
need software developers to to
contribute to
so i think that makes sense i think the
other side
also and something i benefited from a
lot were humanities classes
like i think a big part of starting a
company is communication
writing ability to be able to craft a
story and a pitch to investors
so i think like that you know i didn't
do as much at mit i mean he's not really
known for its um
english classes but especially growing
up you know spent
a lot of time just writing essays and
communication was super valuable for
starting a company as well
and on the other end of the spectrum do
you feel that folks who
want to start a company or want to join
a startup need a cs degree like are you
hiring for people that don't have cs
degrees
for software positions for sure yeah i
think
you know you don't necessarily know have
to know how assembly
language works to to write great
software and
many of our best software engineers at
log rocket don't have cs degrees or even
bachelor's degrees
so 100 i think you can be an amazing
software engineer without a cs
background
or any real formal education for that
matter so if you don't have
friends that you've known for years and
you don't have college
where are people finding their ideas
like so you had said that
you had your first idea with your best
friend at
in third grade where are there areas
that folks could be looking for startup
ideas if they want to start thinking
about starting their own company
the original way we came up with log
rocket was an idea i had working at
this startup so i think the best place
is by
exposing yourself to a set of of
problems that
are unique you know and that might mean
you know say if you're an engineer
maybe try working closer with the sales
and marketing folks for
a couple quarters or a couple years or
join a chemical engineering company
broadening your horizon of the types of
problems you work on i think can really
help expose you to different sets of
ideas i think the other thing is
building relationships with like a
diverse set of people
so i think people are spreading out a
lot more from the valley but you know
being in boston
get a chance to talk to a lot more you
know people doing phds or
people pursuing finance or art you know
so i think
kind of having communities of different
types of people has really helped
broaden sort of my purview into the
world and sort of the types of problems
that
that should be solved yeah and you touch
on a good point about exposing yourself
to
a lot of different people and a lot of
different ideas that sounds like a good
idea for finding a co-founder if you
didn't have somebody who was your best
friend since yeah preschool
how would you have gone about finding a
founder would it have been through
something like your co-workers how how
would you have
sussed that out the best place is likely
joining a
fast-growing business with great great
people you know like one of our
goals at log rocket is that eventually
when we go public someday or
you know who knows what happens that
it'll be a place that people have formed
friendships and they can go on to start
companies of their own and i think you
see that now with a lot of the great
silicon valley companies like airbnb and
coinbase
that people are taking the ideas they
learn from those companies and and
starting their own
especially it's hard with covid but you
know i know there's a lot of different
types of meetup groups to go to where
you can
form friendships there or even just
reconnecting with college friends you
know i
i stay in touch with probably like five
college friends but there's so many
people that
you know reconnecting with them seeing
what they're doing i think that's a
great
great source of people as well you for
your sake you had
a close friend and you guys stayed in
touch over many years and so catching us
back up to the story
you are at your apartment that you're at
for the summer
while you're both at your internships
and you start your idea for log rocket
my first question for you is okay so
you've got that first idea how did you
know it had legs
because it's one thing to go oh i've got
an idea and
so many times i mean i think of ideas
and i immediately either shut them down
or i i post them to somebody else and i
say what do you think about that idea
and they
think of all the reasons why it's not
gonna work so how did you know
that this one was good enough that it
shut off your brain saying i don't know
if this is a good idea to
actually we should keep going with this
yeah you know ultimately
only ideas that have ever worked for me
are ones that i myself have experienced
the problem intimately and know
i'm not so unique in this world there
must be at least a thousand
probably a hundred thousand people just
like me who are experiencing the same
exact problem
you know actually the original idea that
we did in the living room
at 10 pm brainstorming wasn't log record
at all it was a
whole different idea about updating apps
that are in the app store automatically
but i had built enough mobile apps to
know that that was a
really important problem to solve and
there were going to be people and
companies that
would invest in that so any time that
i've tried doing idea that i
myself would not personally use or
benefit from
i haven't been successful but when i
focused on pain points that i myself
know really well
it's worked out so obviously that's like
a survivorship bias but that
has kind of been my guiding light for
how to choose ideas and
make decisions there right but that's an
important point that
you noticed the opportunity where either
you could run into failure later on or
that
to your point of pursuing your passion
really and finding a problem that you
thought was worth solving
you quickly found out pretty early that
that wasn't gonna work and in fact you
said you pivoted nine times
yep so that that first idea we actually
we actually got that up to about 5000
mrr in a couple months so
we started it kind of midway through the
summer and by the end of the summer
we had almost 100 customers but we
didn't feel like that idea had kind of a
long-term potential
because we were essentially
circumventing the apple
app store review process so they were
sort of like legal and compliance
issues that we felt could affect us with
that particular
project i mean we just didn't feel like
we want to invest years of our life just
to have one day
we wake up and apple has shut us down so
that's when we started pivoting and by
the time we started pivoting we'd
actually already raised
a round of venture capital so we
had some time to kind of figure it out
and go through this process of
trying different ideas until eventually
we tried a bunch of ideas that we
ourselves didn't really have a personal
connection with
so we went all the way back to another
pain point that i had
that was a founding idea behind log
rocket and that's what ended up working
for us
i want to dive into that one particular
piece you said which was
we had raised money and when we ended up
pivoting later
this is super fascinating to me i'd love
to learn how do you convince someone
to give you money on a thing that could
change any day
that to me seems remarkable honestly
that you can convince someone that you
can
you can give them money for something
that you don't know if it totally has
legs so how are you able to convince
folks in those very early stages of
fundraising
i think a lot of that comes back to
storytelling and especially early on
investors are not necessarily saying
this is the idea that's going to go big
they're really believing in you
as a person as a team and we knew we
were going to have to make some changes
to
to build a long-term business so our
investor kind of was on board with that
idea that it was going to take us
some iterations to get to where we need
to be and it was
also a small amount of money for this
particular investor matrix partners
you know they have a half a billion
dollar fund if they're investing point
one percent or point zero one percent
in one company they're not really
investing that much
to to this idea so it's almost like
if we go buy a fifteen dollar entree and
it's really bad
you don't feel that upset about it you
know because it's it's a small enough
amount of money relative
to to other things but if you buy a 150
house and it's really a garbage house
you feel really bad about it so
i think there's like an order of
magnitude where below a certain point
the investors don't get affected by
losing that money and that that was
helpful that we found investors with
deep enough pockets that
they weren't upset that the original
idea didn't work and now we're gonna
have to try some different things
yeah and you touched on a really good
point which for the folks listening at
home
i've now collected already three awesome
nuggets of advice
which i've heard from many other folks
and i think you're just saying exactly
the same thing which only
adds validity to it you know the first
one is solve a problem
that you want to solve yourself having
passion around the problems
is a huge thing i've heard that so many
times but it's great to hear you say it
because it really puts validity to it
the second thing is about finding people
you really work well with
whether it's through you know finding a
diverse group of people where you can
share ideas or spread out the duties
that's a really good thing but as you
would said you know you spent a lot of
time with ben
before you ever started a company so you
had a lot of trust in each other
and then the third thing which you just
mentioned was that
you don't necessarily have to have a
good idea so much as you have to have
a great team that people can invest in
because they're not investing money
necessarily in the idea they're
investing money in the people to turn
that idea into reality so
and i've heard that many times as well
too that if you have a great team it can
almost
supersede a product in that sense
because if you have really good people
you can effectively build anything right
and lots of companies pivot
for folks listening at home those those
are definitely things you should take
away
from thinking about you know any
roadblocks you might think about and
trying to start a company
but i wanted to get back to the point
about the pivots so
you obviously had already raised money
before you pivoted onto the actual log
rocket idea
how did you know that you needed to stop
pivoting that you said okay
this is the log rocket we want to build
and this is something that we can
actually take and run with
i remember probably the night before we
came up with
the log rocket idea we were working on
another idea we had been up for
all night and probably multiple days in
a row preparing for this presentation
for this other idea and we gave the
presentation and
this was to one of the investors and
they were like this is just a bad idea
guys like
you need to move on after that we said
we're gonna have one more idea this is
the one we're gonna go
all in on you know it's this or bust and
we went back to the white board we
thought through
first of all what are the changes in the
world that will enable a new company to
be built
and then we came up with this change
around
front end development around more and
more moving to front end and react and
and drop in angular and view we said
that's going to be the change
what are the problems that are now in
that world that we ourselves know
intimately well and that's where we came
up with the troubleshooting
bugs idea i think going back and this is
a big value in in our company today is
thinking from first principles
we took a step all the way back to the
beginning and said like what's the
change
what's the problem and then once we saw
that
and we said we're not going to change
we're going to go deep in this idea
and we spent the next year just building
it honestly you know people say
oh launch early but we spent a whole
year just from that point
building it you know making the
marketing website preparing for launch
and ultimately having conviction in that
idea let us
go through that full year without
needing to pivot or question ourselves
but
that was going to be the last idea you
know if that one failed we were probably
going to pack it up and
fight you know try to apply for a job at
google it's amazing that
so many companies i mean i even just
read about airbnb because they went
public and then paul graham released a
article about how tenacious airbnb was
in the very early days and they said
something very similar which was
we essentially were down to our last bit
of money they maxed out a bunch of
credit cards
and then they had to start making cereal
boxes for themselves just to be able to
afford to pay rent
and airbnb they were on its literal last
legs it's
amazing to me that these companies that
they have you know their last legs and
they're able to turn it around
so what was your first signal for
success now you're on your ninth pivot
but now this is the one so what gave you
the indication that
this time was for real you know i wish i
could say we had everyone say oh this is
a great idea and we go to conference
because we would go to react conferences
and show people the idea and people
would say oh that's cool
you know it's interesting you know how
about this or this product or
you know can't you solve it this way so
i wouldn't say there was a ton of
external validation like it still
for a very long time just came
internally i think where we really
started believing was
my co-founder ben implemented stripe
into our product where you could
basically people could just sign up and
self-serve
to buy sessions with us and the first
time a customer
without ever talking to us you know
signed up went through the 14-day trial
and put in their credit card
that was like wow this now seems like
it's going to work like people are going
to do this
and sign up and and use the product and
that was the moment where
we really believed we had something but
it took a year just to get to that point
it was a year where we didn't know if it
was going to work and sometimes we say
oh
you know maybe people just don't care
enough yeah and i think that comes back
to your passion
point because the truth is even that's
not really
truly success right like just because
you have one customer doesn't mean you
can afford rent or that you can
pay the bills right but just having that
faith
that okay we made it all the way this
far to someone actually paying us money
without having to
basically like twist their arm to get
money from them and they want to use it
i think that's a really good validation
point and sort of a good next step
so now that we have landed on this i
actually just want to know
like for the audience what is log rocket
like the the ninth
iteration version of lock rocket that
you landed on what what does it do today
yeah so the way to describe it is we're
a
front end monitoring solution so we
basically capture
everything users do on the front end of
your application and there's two main
ways people use it one is if someone has
an issue on your site
that you can't reproduce you're able to
go search for that person
and basically watch a video of their
experience and see
technically what happened to them and
then the other way is that
we're actually proactively surface
issues that people are having
so if they're trying to click the add to
cart button and nothing's happening
we're running machine learning
algorithms to actually detect that
negative experience
and surface that to you so you can be
more proactive about fixing
user experience issues and was that what
was on launch day i mean obviously the
product has iterated
many times since then but i'm just
curious what subset of that was the
first one that people said oh i want to
do the 14-day trial and then
pay you guys money yeah it was really
really simple it was just
a user would have a problem and you
could go find their session so it was
from the beginning and actually the
first three to four years we were
focused on just a single problem and i
remember
i'd repeat this again and again to the
team of we help developers solve bugs
faster like that's all we'd say we had
on the whiteboard
people would come to us with other types
of feature requests and product managers
but we just kept focused on that single
problem which was around
when a user submits a support ticket how
do you figure out what happens at user
and solve their issue as quickly as
possible
right and when you say session are you
actually talking about someone can pull
up a video and they can actually see
what the
person did exactly yeah so we actually
basically instrument the dom
from the front end and then capture all
the changes that happen
in the user interface and then we take
those and we recreate what the user saw
so it's almost like you're watching a
video and sitting over their shoulder
you're seeing where their mouse is
what they're clicking on and so you're
able to go back and
it's especially helpful when you have
less technical end users who can't
send videos or or really communicate
what they did you're able to just go
pull up their session and see their
experience
so you actually see the real browser
because i feel like i have experience in
front end and i
in my professional career have mostly
been a front-end developer so a lot of
this speaks to me
and one of the first things i'm thinking
of is oh well i need to actually know if
they're in ie or
they're in chrome or they're on their
phone because right like
your point about being able to sit
behind their shoulder i mean
that is exactly what developers do for
themselves right if someone's trying to
debug a problem and they
ask the senior engineer to come over to
their desk that's exactly what they do
they look at their screen and see
what happens so i think that's a
speaking to your point of solving
developer problems and helping
debug bugs faster my first thought is
like oh well
i.e especially when you started log
rocket ie was the bane of everyone's
existence on the front end could you get
that kind of level of granularity on the
sessions
yeah so we support ie 11 and newer so
that's definitely a big use case
mobile you know people go offline and
you don't know
maybe they were just offline and they
had network connectivity issues so
you're able to actually
yes see the browser they're on see all
the network details
all the console logs and errors we also
capture browser performance information
like memory usage cpu usage and crashes
so there's a lot of information that
just like yeah just like if you open the
dev tools
sitting with someone so i can imagine as
a developer
you've got that slogan about helping
developers solve bugs faster
and then i can see like a video
on your home page of walking through a
session is that how the
launch actually started because you
mentioned that your big part of your
time was spent
just creating and crafting this ideal
setup so that when you launched you
would have everything
all your ducks in a row so what did the
actual launch look like what was that
sort of first version that you put up on
on the site
that's exactly what it was basically
walked through that exact problem that
we had as developers
tried to communicate as clearly as
possible and then
i believe the first version was just an
email signup where
you could put in your email to sign up
to know when we launched and then we
would
reach out for beta users but we
coordinated a big launch on hacker news
and product hunt and
reached out to all our old users had all
our friends ready to kind of help
upvote our contents so we did a big
coordinated push and it ended up
i think driving probably the first
thousands you know emails to us and then
we
kind of use those to to get off the
grounds how did you know you're ready
once we hit the one year mark and i
think you're starting to kind of
wonder like okay maybe it's time we
should really
kind of push it out you know it's it's
dragging on a bit
and we weren't actually completely ready
in terms of the products
it wasn't quite there but we knew it was
maybe two three months away
and this was going to be a good forcing
function too you know we could set a
date
this is one we're gonna launch by we
have to get ready and then
we set that goal and it was a lot of
work obviously you know we would
probably code from 10 am to
6 pm and then we'd go back we were
living together we'd cook
blue apron and then in the night we'd
work on the marketing website so there's
a lot of work to get there but
kind of having that date where we had to
launch by was really the forcing
function
that's why i wanted to ask you know when
you you hear about the entrepreneur that
just started it over a weekend and
you've got to launch early and if
there's that old advice of if you launch
when you're comfortable you've launched
too late
and it sounds like you were ideating on
it for quite a while and you just
basically said okay
one year is just too much we just it
almost sounds like it was arbitrary
other than
the fact it's like okay it's been a
calendar year and we really need to
get our ducks in a row so you weren't
quite ready but
ready enough so how did you know to
carefully coordinate with
hacker news and and product hunt what
was your sort of strategy behind that
at that point didn't really know another
way to get users besides post on hacker
news i thought that's where
that's the only place you could find
products was hacker news in my minds
so it was really our only option of how
do we get users
and we had done some coordinated
launches on the past for hacker news and
those
and had seen success so that's how it
came about you know since then we've
kind of developed new marketing channels
and strategies but
i think it's a great way to get started
as a hacker news post especially
back in 20 i guess this was 2016 2017
where
hacker news was really vibrant kind of
before reddit took off
yeah i mean this year felt like it was
five years so that you know 2016 feels
like it was
two decades ago so easily yeah and a lot
of things have changed so if someone is
listening today
what are those things you've learned i
guess it's really two questions one do
you actually need to have a big launch
event
and if you don't what things would you
teach others today that they could learn
from your mistakes
as to how to successfully launch beyond
just posting a hacker news
you don't necessarily need a big launch
but you might as well
because it's one of those types of
things you really only do it once or
twice
it works reasonably well to generate
interest
so i definitely encourage people do it
on top of that though i'd say
really think just as much as you think
about your product think about the
distribution channels
and that's something we thought about
from the beginning of
it's great if you can build a product
but if no one can find it it's like if a
tree falls in the woods and no one sees
it did it even fall
so equally important to the product is
the distribution and
just as we were thinking about
developing this product we were thinking
about our marketing strategy and how we
would bring it bring it to market and
specifically we were
focused on building out our front-end
blog for front-end developers
so that would be my other advices
depends on the market and what you're
going after but
um really when you're putting together
your plan for what to build
unless you have a way to reach users and
acquire them it's not really a product
and there's benefits and drawbacks by
the way to your to your point about
knowing your audience and finding the
right distribution channels what i've
found
as a plus for somebody like yourself is
you are a developer
and you're speaking to developers so you
know them better than anybody else
because you are one so you have that
advantage
of developing a developer tool right
the downside i think which i'm sure you
know right off the top of your head is
well developers have put a lot of
scrutiny onto things so
you know your audience and you also know
that your audience is
putting a very sharp lens over what
you're building
so there's benefits and drawbacks to
every audience but i think the
the resonating message is if you are not
your target audience you have to find
them
and go where they go right because
hacker news is for hackers it's for
software developers it's for people
in product right but hacker news may not
be the right place if you're building
you know say something for chemical
engineers like you said so do you have
any advice on sort of
finding the right people for those
distribution channels
it depends on what you're going after i
think we've done a content
strategy here at log rocket because as
front-end developers
i would be searching react component
props
day in and day out so half of your job
as developers just searching for things
i would kind of think through the same
for a chemical engineer i'm actually my
partner is a chemical engineer so i
would just ask her but
whoever your audience is ask what their
day to day looks like
are they searching for things do they
read their emails from people trying to
sell them things do they
pick up their phone what does the
day-to-day look like of the person
you're trying to sell to and then how
can you insert yourself
in there with your product but first and
foremost it has to solve an important
problem for them it has to
have an aha moment where they say wow
this is going to solve a big problem for
me
but definitely kind of thinking about
their day-to-day and where you can
insert yourself
and in some cases there's no way to
insert yourself that you may not want to
build for that audience if you can't
actually get in front of them in a
efficient way that's good advice and i
think you brought up a good point which
was
solve an important problem for them i
would add is a big enough problem that
they're willing to hand you a check
because as you said the sort of aha
moment for you guys
was that you had someone who you didn't
know who found you
who signed up for the 14-day trial and
then paid money
so that's a really strong signal that
you're on to something there so there's
a big
gap between your first checks
from matrix the launch of that first
sort of version of pivot nine of log
rocket to today where you've raised 30
million dollars so
i'd love to dive in more to that sort of
fundraising piece we sort of touched on
a little bit earlier
but i'm really curious how did you get
to that next level of fundraising so
you've got your initial
investments you built something people
actually want to pay for it
you've got a version of log rocket that
you know you want to pursue
how did you get to that next step yeah
it's interesting once you have that
first customer
then it's all about customers it's all
about how many customers are you
solving and how much are they paying you
is really the function of
for better worst that's the amount of
value you're creating for for people
so to get to the next that fundraise we
were laser focused on hitting our
revenue goals and
and growing our marketing and in our
customer base
and so you know that first customer took
us about a year to reach
maybe 100 customers somewhere like that
and at that point
that's when we started getting momentum
2.2
hey if we start raising money we can
invest more in sales and marketing and
more in engineering
and keep grow this even faster and at
each point it just makes sense
you know if we had that extra extra
dollar to spend
we're going to create so much value with
it that it makes sense to keep
fundraising and keep
growing what we have but but yeah really
after our first customer it all became
about growth
and you earlier said you mentioned mrr
for the folks listening
what does that mean and how did that
influence
you know when you knew you could raise
more money because a lot of people talk
about especially in subscription
services that mrr is a very key
indicator
for being able to either raise more
money or show growth yep so mri is
monthly recurring revenue so
that's essentially if you have a
customer paying you 99 a month
your mrr is 99 and what investors are
looking for is not necessarily the
absolute amount of mr you have but the
growth rate of it
because if you could take mrr from a
thousand to ten thousand a month
they say wow if they can do that a month
imagine what they can do in
a year and two years and three years
really the
biggest focus for us was making sure
each month we were adding more mrr than
we did in the previous month
right so then once you started to see
reasonable growth numbers or numbers
that you felt were predictable
how did that translate into okay we need
to raise x amount of money how do you
pick that number
it kind of turns into a financial
problem of
we have this marketing channel be it
you know ad spend or content
and we know it's going to translate into
this amount of dollars of mrr
so my co-founder ben actually now runs
our finance function
basically put together these huge
spreadsheets of we invest a dollar here
we're going to get out xmrr you know
eight months later or whatever it is
and basically we use those spreadsheets
to to determine how much we need to
raise
how much runway that's going to give us
as a business if we're burning money
and then you know using headcounts and
the other costs that we have to
basically
figure out how much we're burning each
each month in each quarter
to know when we have to to raise next so
a lot of it is
basically it turns into a financial
problem and you know the input is
expenses and the output is revenue at
the other side okay that makes sense
and the next question i have on top of
that is now you know how much you need
to raise
and is it true that 18 months runway is
about what you want to target if you're
a founder and you're looking to figure
out how much do i need to raise in
advance to
to support that potentially you know i
think it varies
ben and i have always targeted longer
runway than that just because
it always takes longer for things to
work than you think they will and i
think our first ideas
took us two years to reach our first
customer so if we had just raised 18
months of runway
we wouldn't exist right now so i always
encourage people
raise a bit more than they think if you
can get away with it raise 24 months of
runway or 30 months or 36 even
especially now with so much money in the
vc markets i think you're best off if
you can raise enough that
maybe 18 months you need another year to
kind of get to the next stage
you're better off as the entrepreneur if
you've raised that extra money
prior and i think the really important
thing it just is funny because i'm
looking at the notes here and it's
you've raised 30 million dollars and you
have to understand there's this like
whole thing
in the entrepreneurial vc world where
you see the
dollar amount right like company raised
x amount of money and people just like
assume that's like oh well matt's a
millionaire now he just raised 30
million dollars and
he and his co-founder split it halfway
but it's absolutely not that way right
like
all that money has to last that entire
time so if you're raising
30 million dollars in one go for three
years you can only spend 10 million a
year and on top of that
you have to support all the people that
you are employing
and as you mentioned earlier i think you
said a lot of it was going into
marketing
and certain sales channels so tell me
about you know what actually happens
when you get that money where are you
spending it on and
how do you ensure that you you know can
support the system that you're trying to
build
yeah that's a great point it's really to
grow the team and there's so many
expenses that go into a business
you look at rent for the real estate if
you're an employee headcount expenses
you're getting lunches for employees
there's so many different expenses that
you can
that you figure into and that like you
said you have to have to last for years
and years
plus all the growth that you want to
achieve so all the new people you want
to hire
the recruiting efforts the recruiting
resources needed to hire those people
so basically it's you know again another
big spreadsheet everything kind of just
turns into spreadsheets and engineering
problems at the end of the day and
sort of cash management is one of those
problems and then on the other side
the best case scenario is that you don't
need to spend that money that
your customers can fuel your growth so a
lot of our focus has been also of
identifying inexpensive channels where
our customers
we can take you know the customer
revenue and turn that into
reduce the amount that we're burning up
that 30 million and use that more as
sort of a backstop
to achieve growth is that a weird pivot
because i feel like
for folks that are brand new to starting
a company you know they're thinking
about like
being in the garage writing code until
four a.m in the morning and now you're
talking about
spreadsheets and accounting and all this
stuff that
is not the sort of main thing that
software developers are thinking about
when they're starting their own software
company so
is that is that a weird transition like
how much of your time do you spend on
the things that are not software related
i'd say a hundred percent now if i try
to code i invently break something
and people get the engineers on my team
get scared if i ever try to make a code
change or even
suggest code changes so i've removed
myself from that
it's definitely a transition where in
the early days i'd write code 95 some of
the time
to now zero percent but at the end of
the day
you're still building systems and you're
solving problems and i think
if you're starting company it's
important that you or at least your
co-founder is passionate
just about problem solving in general
because
past that kind of initial product market
fit or even during finding product
market fit
so much of it is not just about coding
it's about
customer discovery and marketing and
idea validation and fundraising so
i think it's almost more important to be
excited about those things than it is
about actually
writing code if you just want to write
code probably starting a company is not
the best thing for you or at least make
sure you have someone who's interested
in
the actual process of building a company
on your team that's a really important
point is
balancing the positives with the with
the downside so tell me about some of
those problems that you faced
along the way once once you got log
rocket started i mean
just because you raised a bunch of money
and you got that initial validation
clearly it wasn't just smooth sailing so
what kind of traps did you hit along the
way
yeah obviously covid um is a kind of
through everyone for a loop and
we've really invested a lot in a great
culture of log rocket and an in-person
in-person team definitely was a
transition for everyone to
to go to working alongside your dog in
your
your one bedroom apartment which is
where i am now
but so i'd say you know covered was
definitely one of them
as first-time founders a lot of it was
figuring out what we didn't know
that you learn a year or two years later
and you you'd wish like if only i'd
known that this was going to be a
problem
i wish i'd addressed it a year earlier
so one of those things for us was
starting a sales team i didn't know that
sales was a thing when we started the
company and
you know kind of waited too long to
actually start a sales i
i just thought developers just find
products and they signed up for and they
put in their credit card
i didn't realize i was the one sales guy
just answering
intercom tickets that was something
where okay now i understand the value of
sales and
especially in larger companies so much
process is needed to procure software
so many stakeholders so
all those things that i didn't know that
i wish i'd incorporated earlier on
would have saved us so much time from
the mistakes that we've made so yeah
like starting a sales team is one
certain hiring decisions where i think
it's so important to trust your god and
and
i think you alluded to this of find
people that you really just enjoy
working with and you
sort of like you're excited to go and to
work with them every day and
being really deliberate about that is
has been very important for us so
yeah so so many so many mistakes along
the way but a lot of good learnings
how big is your team now we're around 80
people so still still quite small
you know when you were really early it
was you and ben
you could very much be hands on with
every single hire how do you feel now
knowing that you can't actually be there
for every single interview for
a team now that's almost 100 people yeah
i feel pretty good
you know i think that comes down to
really hiring and promoting great
leaders and
a lot of it comes down to the first few
people we brought into the company and
also
you know recent leaders we brought in
having a lot of trust
in their judgment it gives you so much
peace of mind to know okay they're going
to own their operational area and i can
have a lot of trust in what they're
doing so i'd say that
and i'd also say really establishing
clear a clear culture and values when
making decisions and
being consistent with the way we
evaluate people
and look for greatness i think has
helped us you know but you don't hit 100
there's always misses and you know
sometimes it doesn't work out but
i'd say those two things have really
helped us build consistency in hiring
so we know what the roadblocks now were
for you along this journey
when is it not a good idea to start a
company like
when should engineers not start
companies because you as yourself
said you had two failed companies prior
so what were the signals that you should
said
actually you know i don't think this is
the right company to start if at all you
know honestly
knowing what i know now there's so many
difficulties to starting a company that
i think even for myself
my naiveness five years ago is what let
us get to this point
now i know how how difficult it's going
to be you almost have more reasons not
to start a company than you do to
actually start a company
really good reasons to start a company
are you enjoy
you enjoy building and you have a
problem that you
know has to be solved now like there's a
timely thing
if there's not a change in the world
that will support your idea
and you don't have personal conviction i
would i would avoid starting a company
maybe wait and maybe kind of expose
yourself to new experiences before
diving in
do you think it's binary though because
one thing i was i've been really
thinking about lately is
there's this whole group of sort of like
indie hackers like that's a whole site
about this
where you know you can start a small
company and
you're just constantly working nights or
weekends like there are
uh i think it was sidekick was one of
them it's like a ruby plug-in that
essentially was just open source and
then at some point they decided to
release an enterprise version and now
the guy makes like 80 grand a month
on just this sort of open source side
project and i know
cyprus the front end framework just
raised like 40 billion dollars
and that was purely an open source
project so do you think there's room
for the companies that aren't quite vc
ready but
you know they have enough passion and
conviction that they want to keep going
with it
you know part time definitely even log
rocket our genesis was we were in school
and working on it
between classes or in the back of the
lecture hall you know on my laptop
coding i think you can make a lot of
progress
especially if you don't have other
distractions in life i think it's really
hard when you
have a job or supporting a family you
don't have
all sorts of social activities like it
can be very hard to balance
more than two things i can i think can
be difficult but if you're able to
you know have your job and also pursue a
side project i think that's a great way
to get started or
if you're in school that's a great time
to explore ideas and
you guys are really a safe a safe place
to to try things and fail
that being said i think especially in
developer tools the space we're in
there's sort of a minimum bar of effort
that you have to put in to get
past what a developer can do themselves
so there was
i think certain ideas you have to commit
to or at least really
invest know you're going to spend years
and years working on this problem
because you need to reach a certain
level before it's going to be valuable
to other people
yeah that's a really good point and i
appreciate the advice because as someone
who has
a child and a day job and is doing a
side project like this
it sounds like i've got a big uphill
battle to face it's not purely binary
right like not everyone has to raise 100
million dollars and become facebook to
become a successful company there's
plenty of people who can
do this on the side and make it work but
i think to your point it's just about
balancing those things like if you have
a product that requires a lot of polish
just understand that
it might take you several years to
launch as opposed to
you know some of these like fanciful
ideas where they could launch in a
weekend well
that clearly has a very different bar
for what the customer is looking for
than like you said something in
developer tools space so
the last thing i kind of wanted to pivot
on around this topic sort of like the
part-time
work is also around the topic of remote
you talked about this earlier that
kovid's obviously been a challenge for
not just your team obviously for
everybody it's been
a massive challenge and it's almost
impossible to avoid any podcast without
talking about
kovid right now how is your company
pivoting
on this we were talking about pivots how
are you pivoting in terms of
being a remote organization is that
something you want to continue with are
you going to invest in a hybrid option
you mentioned that
having an in-person culture was super
important
and super valuable for the folks that
you have on your teams how are you
thinking about this going forward
we're still seeing how things play out
that being said i think
you know a big part of why i have always
loved working at startups is the group
of people you're working with and you
just don't get the same
vibe or value from it when you're just
staring at zoom all day and talking to
them
so i'm a big believer in at least having
the option
like i consider work like one of the
places i enjoy going and
talking to people and having lunch and
you know
hanging out or i'm a big believer in at
least having that as an option
but really since the early days we've
believed and sometimes you just need a
place to focus
and i think home is a great or you know
your home office
is a great place to be able to just like
sit down solve a problem
no distractions but i am a big believer
in having a place
to go that's like a community and
something you enjoy waking up and
commuting in for
so if a founder starting today what
advice would you give them about
the options they have certainly remote
has become
more prevalent at companies than it was
a year ago or even six months ago
if you were starting today how would you
think about that equation yeah 100 i
would build your team in person
still i think especially the early team
it's just fun to
have a small team that you enjoy going
into the office with and talking and
hanging out after work that's where so
many of the best ideas come from when
you're a small group
of people i think once you get past a
certain point then you can start to say
like
maybe the talent when we hire the
distributed workforce will be
worth the kind of loss of that culture
and that kind of
comes down to the specific business and
types of people you need and where the
talent is
and also where you yourself are located
i think
having like the first 10 people be able
to be in an office together and hang out
and
do fun things is what at least was super
valuable for us and i think it'd be hard
to recreate that
over zoom and with all the competition
out there which
is never ending in the software space
how do you find those first 10 people
because i would imagine
you're competing against salaries like
google you're also competing against
missions of other small startups
so there's a lot of competition out
there and on top of that you have to
find really great people because as you
said earlier
it's those first few people that really
set the tone for the rest of the culture
i mean that sounds like it's really
arduous because you've got so many other
factors playing into getting those first
few people
how did you make that work we were
really careful about
not hiring until we had traction with
our idea and
some amount of conviction i think it it
helped that we're building a developer
tool
so developers we'd reach out to
developers say hey we're hiring you know
we have some initial customer traction
and they would say this is a product i
would use and love
and that really helped us initially so i
think a lot of it comes down to
the founding team you should hopefully
be able to get to some amount of
traction
and then you can use that traction
momentum to then hire more folks
if the idea is really good and people
believe in it and they can have like a
personal relationship to it
i think that really helps for hiring
people past the founding team the first
10 who
yeah i think are the most critical hires
you know obviously every higher critical
but those
particularly are really important right
so for engineers that want to start
their own software company any last
words of advice for them
don't be discouraged by the naysayers
there's so much advice out there
and so many people who will give their
two cents on your idea and it can be
very
easy to be swayed by their you know
other people but
if you have an idea that you really
believe in and you know is applicable
like i would say just try your best to
tune out the noise or or at least put it
through a filter
and believe in yourself i'd say is the
most important thing because
if we listen to the naysayers we
wouldn't be where we are today and
that's my number one piece of advice
what a great way to end where can we
find out more about you in log rocket
yeah you can check us out at
logrocket.com you can also go to our
blog
blog.loger.com which has some awesome
front-end tutorials
then we also have a actually a podcast
for front-end developers as well
that you can check out that we just
launched pod rocket oh that's a good
play on the
company name i like that it is it is
yeah we missed out on blog rocket so
pod rocket log really does capture a lot
of things in the
software space that's really clever
awesome thanks adam thanks again matt
have a good one
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se-radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin facebook
twitter or through our slack channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
you